My name is Jared Todd.
I'm going to talk a little bit about cleaning off the scale after it's been heat treated and tempered, getting rid of this ugly surface scale, getting it cleaned up and ready to have a handle.
So we'll go ahead and grind a little bit on here.
I'll show you how to take it off, things to look for, things to be aware of.
Now that this is hardened, you have to be careful with how much you grind it and how hard you push on it.
Because you will heat it up to a point where it will lose its hardness.
Once you start getting it cleaned off and you see the shiny metal again, if you're grinding on an edge, and the steel color changes to a dark brown, up through blues and purples, it's gotten soft.
You're going to have to take it back out and you're going to have to re-heat treat it and temper it again.
Don't think that that color is just on the surface. Even if you grind it off, that part of the knife is still going to be soft.
It's going to be a weak spot and as you use it, that spot is always going to get dull and be softer than the other.
So it's worth it to take your time and go slow.
Sometimes it can be, sometimes it will pit a little bit, so that you have to remove some material to get it off.
It's good to just attack it a little bit with a thirty-six grit belt, get most of it off and then finish up with a four hundred and then go to a six hundred.
So that's what I'll do now.
As you can see now, we've started to remove some of the scale from the edge bevel.
This edge bevel hasn't been taken up all the way yet, but I can remove it as long as you watch the temperature and make sure that you don't get it over two hundred and something degrees.
Once you start getting in the three hundred range you start basically tempering the knife.
You start taking out the hardness.
So just take it slow.
It will grind differently, now that it's hardened, than it did when it was soft.
I will feel a little bit more slippery on the belt.
It will feel like it wants to slide around.
Just make sure that you brace yourself and take it slow.